Hello, class. This
lecture will focus
on the pharmacology
of angina pectoris.
So we will review the
pathophysiology of angina.
And with that, if I could
simplify it, is where
there is an imbalance of
oxygen supply to demand.
And if I had to
summarize the main
drugs that are used in angina,
It's going to be the
nitrates, the beta blockers,
and the calcium channel
blockers. So I will review
their mechanism, specific
adverse effects, and
contraindications. And one thing
to know is that it's important
to distinguish which type
of angina the patient
has. So for example, in
vasospastic or Prins metal
angina, we never give a
beta blocker. And the reason
being is the same that we
do for cocaine overdose.
While giving a beta
blocker makes sense because
it's going to block
norepinephrine in the beta
receptors of the heart
and it's going to
decrease heart rate, you
recall that there is going
to be a degree of
unopposed alpha receptors.
So that would actually, if
you gave that medication,
you would actually make
the condition worse.
So we'll go through that.
I will also talk about
ranolazine, which is an
inhibitor of late sodium
channels. and it can be
used for chronic angina.
When we discuss angina and
the possible need for a
PCI or when patients have
acute coronary syndrome,
there is going to be the
need for other medications.
Number one is going
to be the statin
drugs, which I'll talk
about in the next lecture.
There'll be probably the
need to give patients a
drug for hypertension and
we will go through the drugs
throughout the block and
there's also a need for
anti-platelet drugs
especially when we're talking
about post-stenting. So I
will review aspirin, ADP
receptor antagonist and
probably the drugs that are
inhibitors of glycoprotein
2b and 3a in the lecture.
So as mentioned, it's a
two-fold story when it
comes to the chest pain
associated with angina.
Patient has vasospasm or
maybe there is a thrombus
that's going to decrease
coronary blood flow and that is
part of where the chest pain
is coming from. In addition,
to compensate for that.
There's an increase in
heart rate, contractility,
afterload, and preload, and
that enhances oxygen consumption.
And that is the second
player with the chest pain
associated with angina.
One thing about angina is
that that ischemia is in fact
reversible. If somebody has
an MI, then that's where
there is no recovery. You
get damage to the heart.
So this is really important
that we, when we do the
differential, that we establish
what's happening there.
You know, order the EKG,
order the troponin levels.
So with heart rate and
contractility, it makes
sense that giving a beta
blocker in certain angina
conditions makes sense
because we know if we block
the beta 1 receptors in
the heart, you're going
to get a decrease in
contraction and heart rate.
afterload remember that is
like at the ends when the
the ventricle left ventricle
is trying to contract
and let the the blood go
out when we talk about
afterload and wanting to
decrease it and make things
better that is where you
have to give an arterial
vasodilator so that's going
to be true, say, of calcium
channel blockers. Even ACE
inhibitors can do that.
Preload has to do
with venous return. The
more that's going back to
the heart, the more the
heart is going to have to
work. So the idea here is
also you want to decrease
preload. And what does that
very nicely is nitrates.
ACE inhibitors can
also do that, so can
diuretics. But for the
purpose of this lecture,
we're going to talk
about nitrates. And
then the other thing
to understand about
angina and the whole
idea of oxygen supply and
demand, think about it.
If you are losing oxygen,
you're going to shift to
an anaerobic mechanism and
that is going to increase
glycolysis, lactate because
now you're not making
pyruvate since there's a
lack of oxygen you're
making lactate and then the
other thing is that when
the heart is losing oxygen
you're going to get the
accumulation of substance
P and that's going to be
very sensitizing to the
sympathetic nerves and
that too contributes to
the pain that patients
feel when they have angina.
So again, stable angina,
this is angina of
effort. Usually what will
happen is the patient
gets resolution if
they take sublingual
nitroglycerin or if they
stop the activity the
perfect example is when
in the winter you have a
patient who's shoveling
the snow and they start
feeling chest pain if they
had stable angina that
episode should terminate
once they stop the
workload or if they take a
fast-acting nitrate Okay,
so with stable, you
manage with nitrates,
beta blockers, or
calcium channel blockers.
Vasospastic,
this is interesting. It
can happen spontaneously,
even at night if somebody
is lying down. But it tends
to happen mostly, you know,
when patients exercise.
Again, the response will
be towards nitrates and
calcium channel blockers.
beta blockers, as I
said, you are introducing
the same phenomena as
if you were giving beta
blockers to the cocaine
overdose. You're going
to get unopposed alpha.
And then unstable is
very concerning because
the pain comes on
very unpredictably.
Rest does not do anything
for it and usually when
you have unstable angina
it is a concern because
those patients are at a
higher risk of developing an
MI later on. So that's
where the three plus using
antiplatelet drugs, ACE
inhibitors, or statins are
going to be the standard
of care. And usually you
might have to have a situation
where the patient might
need stenting, because
remember, you are getting
blockage, and that is
causing the ischemic event.
So nitrates.
In our body, through the
action of acetylcholine,
bradykinin, you're getting
release of nitric oxide from the
endothelial cells. and that
has to do with the fact
that arginine in the
endoplasmic reticulum will now
shift that nitric oxide into
the vascular smooth muscle.
And what will happen
is you're going to get
an increase in
something called cyclic
GMP and that is
responsible for relaxation.
So relaxation of the smooth
muscle, it makes sense.
You get basal dilation,
a lowering of blood
pressure. And that is the
principle of nitrates. You
want to increase cyclic
GMP, whether it be through
isosorbide, whether it
be through sublingual
nitroglycerin, whether it
be through amyl nitrate.
so we also want to say
the nitroglycerin they're
nitric oxide donors
and it does make sense
because as I said nitric
oxide comes from the
endothelial cells through
this mechanism of arginine
and uh endothelial nitric
oxide synthase okay
giving a nitrate is a
donor of this okay Okay,
when it's broken
down, it's going to be
denitrated by glutathione
S-transferase and
free nitrate is converted
to nitric oxide.
And another metabolic
release of nitric oxide
is by an enzyme known as
mitochondrial aldehyde
reductase. And this may
seem like, why are we
talking about that? This
is the idea of where
we might expect patients
to become tolerant.
And that will mean,
going back to some of
the introduction
pharmacology principles,
is that in order for
you to get relief with
tolerance, you have to
get an increase in dose.
And when we try to
find out why this is
happening with
nitrates, It may be due
to the depletion of
this sulfur group,
or it might be due to the
fact that this enzyme, this
aldehyde reductase, is
inhibited. So what you want to
do is, if you're using
isosorbide or you're using
something like even a transdermal,
a patch form, you want
to make sure that the patient
has an interval-free period,
about 8 hours. So when I
have given nitrid or patches,
I always tell the patient,
if you put it on, say,
at 8 o'clock in the morning,
that's fine. But at 8 o
'clock at night, take it off
so you have another 12 hours
to be free of the nitrate
so you don't get tolerant.
Overall,
nitric oxide donors
will increase venous
capacitance,
decreasing preload. So
again, that has to do
with venous return.
And with that, you're
going to get less cardiac
output. And that makes sense
because if you're getting
less going in, less is
going to be coming out.
And that does relieve the
workload of the heart,
which we want in a patient
with ischemic conditions.
I'm not going to test you on
specifics but just understand
that the sublingual
nitroglycerin is very common
if patients have stable
angina we usually tell them to
put a tablet under their
tongue and if you think about
under your tongue if you
ever look under it it's very
greenish and that is because
those are the vessels so
putting that formulation
under the tongue make sure
that you void the first pass
effect. It gets right into
circulation and the pain
should be relieved quickly.
One thing about this is
that we tell patients that
after the second tablet
which might be almost maybe
8 minutes or 10 minutes
later if you're not getting
relief it's a good idea to
call EMS because at that
point if it's not working
and then we start to
worry about the patient
having a potential MI, okay?
The other thing is they
come in specific bottles
that are amber colored.
That's where they should
stay in because when the
tablets come in contact
with air, they're going
to lose their effect.
And that's another
thing. Once you open the
bottle, within 30 days,
you have to throw it out
and get another bottle,
okay? Very sensitive.
Severe angina, they
can give intravenous
nitroglycerin in the hospital.
Recurrent, typical,
atypical, you can do oral,
buccal, or transdermal.
Remember, buccal is where
you put the tablet in
that pocket in your cheek.
In heart failure, we
sometimes use nitrates. And
because in that specific
condition, and I'll lecture
on that later, you're getting
a decrease in preload.
And that makes sense
because, as I said, in
somebody who is in heart
failure, you want to decrease
the workload of the
heart as much as possible
because that is, in that
specific patient, that's going
to increase contractility
and make things worse.
You'll also see that in
certain hospital protocols,
I mean, there's a couple of
ways to achieve a lowering
of blood pressure in
unresponsive hypertension.
Sodium nitroprusside can
be used. because number
one, it does have the
venous return reduction
capacity, decreases
preload, but it also has the
added benefit that it will
be an arterial vasothilator.
So it's going to do both.
It's going to decrease
the preload and also
decrease the afterload.
Again, duration, I will
not test you on that. But
just, you know, again,
be aware of the fact that
nitro is coming in certain
formulations. Most commonly,
it's the sublingual. And
then again, if you're
trying to manage somebody
long term, you want to do
transdermal or the oral
dinitrate or mononitrate.
So, the adverse effects.
Throbbing vascular headache.
And this is important
because if we're thinking
about what this medication
is doing, it's vasodilating.
And hopefully you know
from last semester when
patients have migraines,
the problem with the
pain has to do with
vasodilation of the cerebral
arteries. So when we
give somebody a drug like
sumatriptan or Zomig,
we intend for them
to get a quick relief
because they're going
to get vasoconstriction.
And that's a good thing
for the headache patient
because they're going to
feel relief from the pain
rather fast. but one of the
warnings on those drugs is
that you can't take maybe
more than two doses a day
and in a week no more than
six and the reason being
is that vasoconstriction
that it's affording will lead
to an increase in blood
pressure or it can complicate
somebody with angina and
in that population that's
probably not the right way
to go when you're treating
migraines You probably
want to do something more
prophylactic, like give maybe
a calcium channel blocker.
When you vasodilate,
that's going
to bring down your
blood pressure.
And what happens
is the compensatory
mechanism. And I'm
going to say this
throughout all of my
lectures this block.
When your blood
pressure goes down, the
body responds in two
ways. Number one,
it's always going to
want to go back to what
it was. So it's going
to invoke sympathetics.
And the other thing that it's
going to invoke
is the RAS system.
So if it invokes
sympathetics, you're going
to get something called
reflexive tachycardia.
So you need to watch
the patient's heart
rate if you're giving
this type of medication.
The other thing to know
is that with increasing
RAS, patients are going
to have more edema.
So that might be something
that you want to examine
long term. The other thing
is when patients take
nitrates, like if they
were taking the sublingual
nitroglycerin, I always tell
them make sure that they
are seated. Because some
patients have experienced
dizziness and worst case
scenario, they can fall.
So one thing that you'll
see in the reading is
that nitric oxide activates
guanil cyclase, okay?
And that increase in cyclic GMP
can decrease
platelet activation.
But the thing is
that its use as an
antiplatelet is
not established. So
mechanistically,
it does make sense.
But on a clinical
basis, it's a no.
And then the drug interactions
is very important.
because you're giving a
nitric oxide donor that's
going to increase guanyl
cyclase and I've been saying
that and that's going to
increase cyclic GMP and
that's going to cause smooth
muscle relaxation okay
so you've lowered your
blood pressure you hopefully
have decreased the workload
of the heart and the
patient is feeling better
from the chest pain but
the issue is if patients
are also taking drugs for
ED, erectile dysfunction,
like sidenafil, redafinil.
Those drugs, what they
do is they inhibit
an enzyme called
phosphodiesterase 5. And
by doing that, as you
can see right here,
you block this enzyme,
you increase your cyclic
GMP, and that does cause
smooth muscle relaxation
and improves blood flow in
those patients that have
this problem with having
an erection. But if you
had on board a nitrate,
you're almost getting like
a super effect where
there has been cases where
patients get excessive
smooth muscle relaxation, a
severe reduction in their
blood pressure, and guess
what happens? the invoking
of sympathetics. So
early on, before they
really studied this effect,
there were patients who did
die from taking drugs for
ED with nitrates. And that's
going to also be true of
sodium nitroprusside and
to an extent, hydrolazine.
Hydrolazine, again,
I wouldn't worry as
much because hydrolazine
is usually given
in the hospital for
severe hypertension.
But it would be
important that you
let the physician
know about that.
They say that if
you do take nitrates
and you do elect to
take a drug for ED,
they do say that
giving a 48-hour
window of free
nitrate is important.
Okay?
So that's a very
important interaction.
sodium nitroprusside is a
short-acting nitric oxide
donor it's used intravenously
for hypertensive
emergencies it dilates
both arterioles and venules
so as I mentioned it's
going to do both it's going
to decrease the preload
and the afterload so the
venous return and the force
of contraction later on.
One thing about
nitroprusside is very
interesting is that it
has cyanide moieties
in its structure,
as you can see here.
And for the most part,
this is okay if you are
a patient that is able
to excrete the cyanide.
but of course there are
some people who might have
renal impairment and they
may build up the cyanide
and that is going to look
like a cyanide poisoning
where the patient is
going to appear very red
they're going to have
difficulty breathing so what
can be done in that case
two things you can do. You
can do either sodium
thiosulfate, which donates its
sulfur group, being
thiosulfate, to the cyanide,
and that compound will be
excreted from the body.
And the other one
is hydroxycobalamin.
And as you can see,
that is vitamin B12.
And that would mean
that if it picks
up the cyanide, it
becomes cyanocobalamin,
which is another form of B12.
So what happens is if you
don't use it, remember B12
is water-soluble and it
would go out in the urine.
So cyanide toxicity, it's
pretty important if we
want to talk about the
toxicology point. It all has
to do with the fact that
the cyanide will block
something called cytochrome
oxidase. In the electron
transport chain, this
specific enzyme generates
a proton gradient. okay
when it gets blocked by
a cyanide poisoning
you're going to get in the
mitochondria oxidative
phosphorylation cellular
respiration is going to be
stopped and you're shifting
aerobic to anaerobic
metabolism and that's going
to increase lactic acid
the patient will die by
asphyxiation. And the
idea with cyanide,
there seems to be
this connection
between the smell
of bitter almonds.
That's not something that's
so important, but it may
be something that the boards
might test on. So when
I think of bitter almonds,
I always think about
cyanide and this whole
relationship of inactivating
cytochrome oxidase and
causing anaerobic metabolism.
One thing about vasodilators,
and this is going
to be true of all
vasodilators, and also
diapritamol, which I will
talk about a little bit
later, is this idea of
coronary steel syndrome.
and this is an interesting
phenomena because
when you give a vasodilator
to somebody who has
ischemia what happens
is that naturally when
patients have a narrowing
of their coronary
arteries these arteries
are always dilated
so when you give a
vasodilator what happens
the blood will go
away from the ischemic
area and be diverted
back to the normal area.
And that would mean that
in essence the patient
is going to have even more
episodes of chest pain.
So this is something that
you would probably want
to tell the patient If
they have a worsening of
their angina after taking
something like a nitrate,
they should let you know
about that because that
could be something that
might be happening. This
divergence of blood back
to the non-ischemic area.
So calcium channel blockers,
we have two groups.
We have the dihydropyridines
and the non-dihydropyridines.
Calcium is essential
for so many things,
for nerves, smooth
muscle, cardiac,
skeletal, and the
exocrine glands.
For the purpose
of cardiovascular,
we're really going
to talk about
the arterioles and the heart.
The dihydropyridines
are going to
work specifically
for the arterioles.
The non-dihydropyridines
work for the arterioles, but
they also work for the
heart. and with respect to
cardiology these are the l
-type channels back when you did
seizure drugs back in um
I don't know march which
is like a long time ago
I believe you talked
about ethosuximide for
opson's seizures and that
too was a calcium channel
blocker but they were
going to block the t-type
channels in the thalamus
okay these are L-type
channels for the heart.
So as you can see, calcium
comes into the smooth muscle.
Calmalgulin is its
binding protein. And from
there, you're going to get
an increase or activation
of myosin light chain
kinase, kinase is
phosphorylate. This
phosphorylated myosin light chain
combines with actin to
cause contraction of the
smooth muscle. And that
will in fact display as
an increase in blood
pressure. So calcium channel
blockers, as you can see
here, will block that.
On the opposite side, these
are the beta-2 agonists.
I'm not going to cover this,
but this has to do with
drugs such as albuterol and
salmeterol. That will be a
review then later when you
do respiratory physiology.
So calcium channel blockers,
the dihydropyridines,
mainly are going to
be specific for the
arterials. So you're
going to get relaxation,
you're going to get a decrease
in peripheral vascular
resistance, and a decrease
in afterload. So your
blood pressure goes down,
the heart will work less,
and this is the principle
of using drugs like
filodipine or amlodipine for
angina or for hypertension.
Rapid male and diltiazem
I'll go through in depth
when we do the lecture on
antiarrhythmics because
while they can work in
the arterial, they're also
working in the SA node or
the pacemaker and the AV
node. And by doing that,
they're decreasing the heart
rate, automaticity, and
they're also decreasing
the contractility. So the
class 4 antiarrhythmics,
which include verapamil
and diltiazem, can be used
for situations like
supraventricular tachycardias.
They can also be used for
hypertension and angina.
So again, the dipenes,
arterial action only.
They're going to decrease
the peripheral vascular
resistance and the BP.
And because of this, the
dipenes, more so than the
rapamil and diltiazem,
are going to elicit
the sympathetic reflex.
So you're going to see more
tachycardia happening
with these drugs.
I will say that the
later generation,
for example,
amlodipine and folodipine
have less of this
effect, but it still
should be expected. And the
other thing is that
amlodipine and furlodipine
are also used once a
day. So that makes it
very convenient, especially
for patients that
you're trying to treat
high blood pressure for.
Nifedipine can be used in
pregnancy, specifically
when those patients are in
the hospital and they're
about to deliver and their
blood pressure shoots
up, preeclampsia. You
can use nifedipine. You
could also use, I believe,
libetolol. Yes. And there's
also on the list
hydrolyzine. Usually for
patients that are outpatient,
even though libetolol is
getting more popular, they
still give methyl dopa
as first line because
we have used it for many
years and it's effective
and it's not teratogenic.
So the non-dihydropyridines
affect the arterial role,
so you're going to get
smooth muscle relaxation,
and you're also
going to decrease
heart rate and AV node action.
Bromapamil seems to do this a
little bit more than diltiazem.
The thing about these, since
you have something that
is blocking the pacemaker
action in the AV node in
the heart, you're going to
be more prone possibly to
bradycardia with these two
as opposed to the arterial
specific drugs which will
involve more tachycardia.
We can use this as I mentioned
for hypertension, angina,
for certain arrhythmias like
SVT, for AFib, especially
if the patient cannot
tolerate a beta blocker.
The only thing is, and
I'll get into this later,
these two have a negative
inotropic effect.
They have a negative
coronotropic, and remember,
coronotropic applies
to heart rate, and that
makes sense. If it's
negative coronotropic, that
means it's going to
decrease the heart rate.
They decrease inotropic
effect. Inotropic has to
do with contractility.
So if it's a negative
inotropic drug, you're
going to decrease the
contraction of the heart.
This is why these drugs are
contraindicated in
congestive heart failure.
And I'll mention it when
we get to that lecture.
The adverse effects,
the dizziness,
especially with anything
that is going to lower
your blood pressure and
relaxes arterial roles,
whether it be these drugs
or if it's a nitrate, you're
going to get dizziness.
Headache again, why?
Because we're dilating
the cerebral vessels and
that's going to cause more
of a throbbing headache.
And then the edema has
to do with the fact that
you're invoking the RAS
system. So increasing
renin, angiotensin,
aldosterone by now, that
means you're like holding
in sodium and water
follows. So you're
going to get more edema.
Again, tachycardia is
for the dihydropyridines
and then the bradycardia
is for the non
-dihydropyridines. Again,
why is that the case?
Because the rapamyl and
diltiazem are blocking the
action in the heart,
the SA and the AV node.
Constipation, which
tends to happen mostly
with verapamil, has
to do with the fact
that if you're blocking
calcium in the gut,
you're going to
decrease peristalsis.
And that would decrease
the movement, so
patients will become
more constipated.
Gingeral hyperplasia, as
you see in the picture,
an overgrowth of gums,
has to do with the fact
that there is an increase
in growth factors. an
increase in collagen
production and deposition.
And not only is this happening
with these drugs, but
it also happens with drugs
such as phenytoin and,
of course, cyclosporine.
It's always important when
we do these lectures that
we review past material.
Grapefruit juice, very big.
When you take these medications
with grapefruit juice,
what you think might happen,
you're getting inhibition.
So if you were taking
a dihydropyridine like
nifedipine and you're getting
higher levels of the drug,
you're going to expect more
dizziness, more reduction
in blood pressure, and
perhaps reflexive tachycardia.
If you were taking
grapefruit juice
with the rarapamil
or diltiazem, you
probably would have
more bradycardia.
Very important, because
we'll go through
this again in the
antiarrhythmics lecture.
Calcium channel blockers,
especially rapamil, will
reduce the clearance of
digoxin from the kidney.
It affects the transporters
there in the kidney.
So, you'll have more of
an increase of digoxin
levels. And the
digoxin, when we get to
it, is a drug of narrow
therapeutic index.
Just one extra tablet
of digoxin can put your
patient at a risk of
having an arrhythmic event.
If somebody overdoses
on a calcium channel
blocker, you want to
provide supportive care.
You want to watch their blood
pressure and heart rate.
you can give IV calcium
okay especially if we're
thinking about the patient
having more of a bradycardia
and insulin and you know
again this is not going
to make sense right now
but by next semester when I
lecture on diabetes when
insulin is released what
happens is that you're going
to get a shuttling in, very
simply, of calcium into
the pancreatic beta cell.
So, when that happens,
you release insulin.
And insulin is going to
bring down the blood glucose.
Somebody that overdoses on
a calcium channel blocker,
not only is going to have
a problem cardiovascularly,
but they're going to have
hyperglycemia because
that calcium is being blocked
from entering the cell.
So you're not releasing
insulin and the patient
may present with a blood
sugar of like 300 or 400
milligrams per deciliter.
So that's why in certain
protocols, when we talk
about how we manage
these cases, insulin is
on the protocol as well.
So beta blockers,
going back to the SA
node, they're going to
decrease heart rate,
decrease oxygen demand.
That can work if
we're talking about a
patient with angina.
In the ventricular
myocardium, because they're
blocking norepinephrine
at the beta-1 receptor,
you're going to
get a decrease in
contractility. That too
will decrease oxygen demand.
In the resistance vessels,
like the arterioles,
you're also going to
have some effects on
afterload. So that will
reduce blood pressure and
that too can decrease
myocardial oxygen demand.
One thing to know
is that with these
drugs, anything
that works at the
beta-receptor, beta
-1, beta-2, beta-3,
remember going back to
receptor physiology and
we have to review it,
those are G-stimulatory.
So G-stimulatory means
that you're increasing
adenyl cyclase, you're
increasing cyclic
AMP, protein kinase
A, and that's going
to increase calcium
and cause contraction.
and that makes sense
if we're talking about
the heart more calcium,
more contraction,
more workload so
giving a beta blocker
fits well at blocking that
again, just to go back
G-inhibitory, I think the
biggest one if we want to
do a quick review that's
going to be the opioids
GQ would be something
like the alpha 1 receptor
so beta 1 that's
probably the biggest
thing we need to know
with these drugs there's
one heart so beta 1
receptors in the heart
there's two lungs beta
2 receptors in the
lungs beta 1 in the
heart you're blocking
norepinephrine you're going
to decrease heart rate
cardiac output and renin from
the juxtaglomerular apparatus.
So in essence,
even though they're
not RAS drugs,
they do have an
effect at inhibiting
renin. So that's like
an added benefit.
They can be used
for many different
reasons, cardiovascularly,
hypertension,
post-MI, congestive
heart failure,
angina, except
vasospastic. and they're
also class or phase 2
antiarrhythmics because
they decrease the
action in the SA node
beta 1, atenolol,
metoprolol they're very big
in cardiology probably
the biggest effect is AV
blockade this is important
because AV blockade
can bring somebody's
heart rate really low and
being bradycardic is
not a good thing It's
actually just as dangerous
as being tachycardic.
So when you give people
beta blockers, you need
to start out slow and
increase the dose as needed.
You also, again,
don't discontinue beta
blockers abruptly
because that can increase
the surge of
sympathetic overdrive.
Beta 2.
those are considered
to be the non-selective
because they block
beta 1 and beta 2
so metoprolol is
selective for beta 1
propanolol is non
-selective as I mentioned
beta 2 is in the lungs
if you're blocking
beta 2 in the lungs
you're going to get
contraction of the smooth
muscle there so anybody
with asthma COPD is
going to be more prone
to a problem with
respiration and that makes
sense because what do we
use to combat somebody
with asthma, we give a
beta-2 agonist. So a beta-2
antagonist is going to
cause more asthma COPD.
Hypoglycemia, because
beta-2 is in the liver.
When your blood sugar is
down, the beta-2 receptors
tell the liver to convert
glycogen to glucose.
If you're blocking
that receptor
and you become hypoglycemic,
there's no way to increase
your blood sugar. So
somebody, especially that
is relying on insulin,
will have a problem in
getting a non-selective.
And then beta-2 on
the vessels, if you're
blocking beta-2 in the
vessels, that can increase
a patient who has
peripheral vascular disease
because they're going
to get constriction.
Constriction in those
vessels is going
to cause a decrease
in blood flow and
that will complicate
somebody with PBD.
Libetilol and carbetilol,
they're alpha and
beta blockers. So not
only are we blocking beta
1, beta 2, but we're
also blocking alpha. So
you're also getting
the benefit of alpha 1
blockade, which means
you're getting vasodilation.
Pindilol and acebutylol.
Pindilol is non
-selective. Acebutylol is
selective. It can worsen
angina. Why? Because
both of these are partial
agonists. They can
have this intrinsic
sympathomimetic action.
So it's actually
like you're invoking
sympathetics in somebody
that you're trying to
decrease the workload of
the heart for, and that
can complicate. So we
want to avoid those.
Esmolol is ultra-short
-acting. It can be used, for
example, if the patient
has an overdose of, say,
theophylline and we're
worried about an arrhythmia.
Nebevilol, as I highlighted,
is a nitric oxide effect.
So it has two. It's a
beta blocker plus a nitric
oxide action. So you're
getting some vasodilation.
The antidote here is you
want to make sure that the
patient is stable. If you're
getting AV node suppression,
you may need to withdraw
slowly the beta blocker.
And of course, if
you overdose, now you
become hypoglycemic.
The way we manage
hypoglycemia is by
giving glucagon.
So ranolazine, mainly
used for chronic
angina. Okay, this one
is going to inhibit the
late inward sodium
channel in the heart.
And by doing that, you're
getting less sodium in.
And if there's less
sodium in, that means
you're going to get
less calcium in.
Okay, because this exchange
mechanism is going to be
blunted. less calcium in
you're reducing your oxygen
consumption okay so that
would be the mechanism of
this medication but again
it's not going to be given
first line it'd be used for
patients that have chronic
angina and one thing to
know about this particular
medication is that it can
prolong the QT interval.
And that has to do with
the fact that there may
be some blockade of the
heart potassium channels.
So we want to be very
careful about giving this
medication. Okay, because
prolonging the QT interval
can create arrhythmias
in certain patients. The
other thing is that
anything that inhibits SIP,
again, grapefruit juice
or azole, antifungals,
they can increase
this drug's action.
And that, again, can lead to a
higher incidence
of QT prolongation.
So some of the other
therapies, as I mentioned,
PCI, which is stenting. If
the patient has a certain
number of blockages
and stenting is not an
option, you might have to
do a CABG, a coronary artery
bypass. And that is
definitely more invasive.
Anti-hypertensives
are included.
Smoking cessation,
lifestyle modification.
So again, it's not
just about the hard. We
have to watch the
patient's glucose levels.
Antiplatelet drugs I'll talk
about in the rest
of this lecture.
Trimetazidine. You may
see it in the reading,
but it's not available
in the United
States. It has a very
interesting mechanism.
It does inhibit
fatty acid oxidation.
So you're shifting from fatty
acid to glucose oxidation.
And the benefit is
that you are increasing
the heart's use of
glucose. And that does
improve somebody that
has an ischemic event.
But it's not approved
in the United States. I
think it had to do with
the fact that there were
reports of enhancing
Parkinson's disease symptoms.
The other drugs will
be covered in future
lectures because for
the most part, when
you give somebody a
stent, they're almost
always going to go home
with a statin drug.
So with the antiplatelets,
probably the one that
we know the most about is
aspirin. That is, again,
the idea where by
inhibiting psychooxygenase 1
and 2, you stop the
production of thromboxane.
Thromboxane is considered to be
a potent platelet aggregator.
Aspirin's effect
on the platelet is
irreversible for
the lifetime of the
platelet, probably
about 7 to 10 days.
NSAIDs are reversible. They're
not used as antiplatelet drugs.
In fact, giving NSAIDs
together with aspirin at the
same time may actually negate
the antiplatelet effect of
aspirin. So we like to space
it out by several hours.
The other drugs that
you went through are
the ADP receptor blockers
like clopidogrel.
And I'll go through
them in a moment.
Then we have the drugs
that stop the connection
of one platelet to
another. It's a cross
-linking reaction that
happens, and that is due
to glycoprotein 2B3A.
And we have probably
the biggest one is
amphibitide and tyrofibane.
Psilastazol and
diapritamol. And I mentioned
diapritamol because
sometimes we use that
in a stress test
because of the fact that
we want to check how
the heart is pumping.
These are considered to
have vasodilatory effects.
Diapritamol is sometimes
implicated in that
coronary steel action that
I told you early on. And
these drugs are going to
enhance PGI 1, 2. This
is called prostacyclin.
Prostacyclin, very
interesting, very simple.
It keeps things flowing.
Okay.
Where are these used?
Well, usually for
patients that have
intermittent claudication.
These are patients, say,
if they have peripheral
artery disease, especially
if we're talking about
the extremities, they're
going to feel like they
can't walk even down a
block without getting pain.
And that's because
you're getting
vasoconstriction. By
giving something like
psilostasol, you are
going to, in fact,
increase cyclic AMP.
Because these are known
as phosphodiesterase
inhibitors. So
basically, by blocking
here and increasing
cyclic AMP, you are, in
fact, enhancing the
action of prostacyclin.
So again,
aspirin, irreversible.
It's used for
analgesic properties,
anti-inflammatory,
and antipyretic.
Honestly, these are the
uses, but they're not widely
used anymore. Most patients,
and you know, if you
have a fever or you have a
pain because you did a lot
of work at the gym, you're
probably going to take
something like Motrin,
Ibuprofen, or even a Tylenol.
But aspirin does
have those effects at
blocking inflammation
and reducing fever.
ADP receptor blockers,
as I mentioned,
glycoprotein 2B3A, and
phosphodiesterase inhibitors.
One thing to note about
low-dose aspirin is the
fact that it does have
several adverse effects. And
probably the one to be
most noted is a GI bleed.
And for the most part, if
you are well controlled
and you're monitored by
the physician, most people
do fairly well. But there
have been patients in the
past that, you know,
and this has to do with
marketing and advertisement
that pretty much take it
upon themselves to start
taking aspirin therapy on
their own, not checking
with their physician, and
then they end up with
some type of GI bleed. And
because of that, probably
around 2021-2022, they changed
the guidelines where
aspirin prevents primary
cardiovascular disease and
recurrence of secondary.
So, what you want to go back
to is you want to consider
the individual patient,
risk versus benefit. it
you should not be taking an
aspirin regimen when you're
20 to prevent an MI if maybe
somebody in your family
had an MI you need to get
that checked out so what
the physician will do is
they will calculate your
ASCVD score if it's high and
they put all the criteria
then they might give you
go ahead to take a low
dose aspirin okay that has
to do with primary prevention
if you've had an mi a
stroke or angina that's a
secondary prevention then
you should be given the 81
milligram aspirin so basically
no for primary unless
you speak to your physician
and calculate the score,
yes for secondary to prevent
a second MI or stroke.
Aside from the GI bleed,
which has to do with the
fact that you're losing
prostaglandins in the GI
tract, and those prostaglandins
are cytoprotective,
there are patients who
are allergic to aspirin.
Because remember from last
spring when we talked about
the pathway between ***
and LOX, those that are
allergic to aspirin, there
may be a shunting towards
the LOX pathway and that
can cause bronchospasm. In
an overdose, patients will
end up dying of metabolic
acidosis if they're not
given ventilation, if you're
not doing the ion trapping
with sodium bicarbonate.
And that has to
do with uncoupling
of oxidative phosphorylation.
And then of course, aspirin,
which is a salicylate,
It should not be used for
pediatric patients, and
the reason being is the
high risk of Rye syndrome.
These are the, I guess, five
ADP receptor
blockers available.
All of them are pro
-drugs, but Ticagrelor and
Cangrelor. And Cangrelor
is used intravenously.
It's direct acting, just
like Ticagrelor. But
since it's IV, there's
no first pass effect.
It works fast. It's probably
used mostly post-PCI.
What I will say about
these medications
is that post-PCI,
you will probably
want to give two of
these medications.
Usually it's aspirin and
an ADP receptor blocker.
And that is usually continued
for about 6 to 12 months.
I cannot give you an
exact number because some
patients may need a little
bit more than 12 months
and some may need less.
It all depends on the
patient. But post-PCI,
you want to give two
antiplatelets, usually one
of these and the aspirin.
Clopidogrel is
probably the most
popular one. This is a Plavix.
It's oral. It's available
generically. It is a pro
-drug and being a pro-drug
means that it needs to be
activated by something and
it's activated by CYP2C19.
If you are okay with 2C19,
the drug will be activated
and it works. Anybody
that has a mutation or is
taking a drug that inhibits
this is going to have
a reduction of antiplatelet
effect. And one example
is a popular drug known
as omeprazole. It's a PPI.
So if you gave omeprazole
and clopidogrel,
omeprazole will inhibit
2C19 and that will lead to
clopidogrel not being
activated. And that means the
patient will fail antiplatelet
action. So what do
you do? Either you change
the PPI to something else,
or you give another ADP
receptor blocker. You can
give, say, ticagrelor. But
remember, ticagrelor is
probably more expensive
because it's direct acting.
So again, these drugs
can be used for unstable
angina, non-ST elevation
MI, in combination with
aspirin all of them will
prevent thrombosis and
they're considered standard
for patients who have
had a stent they can
also be used for ACS one
thing about them especially
the direct acting is
the bleeding so patients
have to be very mindful
if they see blood in their
stools or when they're
brushing their teeth,
they need to report that.
If they were using an
anticoagulant, that's
a big flag. You have
to make sure that
both classes are
needed. Probably not.
Tyclopidine or tyclid was
probably the first
one developed.
It was a very good drug,
but what happens here is
that it does cause something
known as neutropenia.
And this is not something
that happens rather quickly.
It usually happens within
weeks of taking the
medication. So in this
case, patient would have to
be mindful if they developed
a sore throat, fever,
flu-like symptoms to
report it to the physician.
So why are we talking
about this? Well, probably
you'll never see it in
your practice but boards
still will test this
adverse effect so just be
mindful that this
medication would cause the
neutropenia glycoprotein
2b3a inhibitors again they're
going to stop the fibrinogen
cross-linking between
the platelets absiximab
was a monoclonal it's
no longer available in
the United States, but
you may want to recognize
it in case it's tested.
The reversible inhibitors,
epfibitide and tyrofibane,
they have very short
half-lives. They are
going to be administered
by continuous infusion.
They're usually going
to be given an ACS or
PCI in those that have
a high thrombus risk,
in those that can't
take an ADP receptor
blocker or those with
an aspirin allergy.
So they'll be given this right
after the stenting procedure.
Adverse effect,
again, bleeding.
And then there's a
correlation between this
medication and pathology.
And sometimes on
boards, they may try to
link up to disciplines,
whether it be farm
and micro or farm and
PEF, this one has to do
with glansman disease,
which, as I
understand, this is a
deficiency of
this glycoprotein.
And when patients have this
deficiency through
perhaps genetic,
they're going to be at
higher risk of bleed. And
that makes sense because
inhibitors of this particular
glycoprotein, the drugs,
do cause bleeding.
So it's good to understand
that these drugs
were developed with a
pathology correlate.
So in summary, it's important
that you understand the
types of angina and the
appropriate therapeutics,
especially nitrates, calcium
channel blockers and beta
blockers so I would go through
that and know which type of
angina gets which I would
go through the antiplatelet
medications I will be doing
a question review and I do
believe that those can be
very helpful because again
with pharmacology it's always
a lot of medications so
hopefully you do give a quick
watch to the questions and
of course if you have any
questions please let me know
until then have a great
day and I will see you soon